<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Florian Hartmann</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://localhost:4002/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4002/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 18:19:43 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 18:19:43 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.5.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Recurrent Neural Networks and Long-Short Term Memory</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Yup&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 14:36:20 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4002/recurrent/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4002/recurrent/</guid>
        
        
        <category>machine-learning</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tackling MNIST with deep learning techniques</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Yup&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 14:36:20 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4002/mnist/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4002/mnist/</guid>
        
        
        <category>machine-learning</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What I learned from implementing ML algorithms</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Yup&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 14:36:20 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4002/learning-ml/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4002/learning-ml/</guid>
        
        
        <category>machine-learning</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Differential Privacy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Yup&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 14:36:20 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4002/differential-privacy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4002/differential-privacy/</guid>
        
        
        <category>reading-notes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Understanding Decision Trees</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Yup&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 14:36:20 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4002/decision-trees/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4002/decision-trees/</guid>
        
        
        <category>machine-learning</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bloom Filters</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Yup&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 14:36:20 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4002/bloom-filters/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4002/bloom-filters/</guid>
        
        
        <category>probabilistic-data-structures</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What I read in 2017</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Whenever I’m looking for a new book to read, I really enjoy looking at lists of
books other people read. Since I started reading more again this year, I thought
it’d be a good idea to write down some thoughts on the individual books. I ended
up reading 12 books, picking up a new one nearly every month.
In the following, the books are listed in the order that I read them in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-sense-of-style&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Sense-Style-Thinking-Persons-Writing/dp/0143127799/r&quot;&gt;The Sense of Style&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/books-2017/sense-of-style.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Sense of Style cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sense of Style is a style guide that tries to explain how to write more elegantly and
effectively. I started reading this book in the very beginning of January, when I
was in the final weeks of working on my bachelor thesis. Of course, the timing was not a
coincidence, and I do feel like the book has helped to improve my thesis a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise however, I also ended up finding the book itself quite enjoyable to read. Partly, this
is definitely because it is written in great style, by a highly eloquent author.
While I was reading the book, it also occured to me that I never really thought
about the fact that there are style guides for writing prose, similiarly to how
programmers have style guides for code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book addresses not only stylistic choices but also dives into more psychological
aspects. One of these points that I really internalized is what the author
calls the &lt;em&gt;curse of knowledge&lt;/em&gt;.
By having a deep understanding of a topic, it becomes incredibly hard to explain
it in a good way to people without much prior knowledge. This is due to the fact
that we forget the difficulties we had when first learning about
the topic ourselves. Now it all seems so simple and it’s easy to fall into the
trap of thinking that certain parts are also obvious to other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-signal-and-the-noise&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Signal-Noise-Many-Predictions-Fail-but/dp/0143125087/&quot;&gt;The Signal and the Noise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/books-2017/signal-and-noise.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Signal and the Noise cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of people will probably know the author, Nate Silver, for his incredibly
accurate election predictions. He is also well known for applying statistical
techniques to baseball, and for his articles at
&lt;a href=&quot;http://fivethirtyeight.com&quot;&gt;FiveThirtyEight&lt;/a&gt;, where he combines statistics with
journalism. I have to admit that this impressive biography is also what got me
interested in his book initially. While this is not the best reason to read a
book, I have to say that I really enjoyed it. Over the last year, I ended up recommending
the book to a lot of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each chapter, Silver explains how statistics are used to make
predictions in different fields.
The range of these applications is quite large and goes from elections over
weather reports and climate change to online pocker.
Because there is such a large variety of topics, the book never gets boring. It’s also
interesting to see how complicated things like weather predictions are, while
they are so ordinary for us that we don’t give them much thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started reading the book, my expectations were a bit off, as I expected a
lot more math. Instead, the book is more concerned with explaining the
fundamental ideas on a popular scientific level. This means that the book
contains nearly no math but often gets into psychological aspects. For example,
a good part of the chapter on weather predictions is spent on explaining why some
predictions are made more inaccurate for psychological reasons. This is not
necessarily a negative criticism of the book, as I also deeply enjoyed these topics.
Lastly, I want to mention that the book also contains a really good high-level introduction to
Bayesian statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reinforcement-learning-an-introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://incompleteideas.net/sutton/book/the-book.html&quot;&gt;Reinforcement Learning: An Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/books-2017/rl.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reinforcement Learning: An Introduction cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinforcement learning is a subarea of Machine Learning with some essential
differences to (un)supervised learning. The fundamental idea is that we want to
train an agent that learns how to perform tasks in a dynamic environment. In
contrast to supervised learning, the feedback given to the agent is delayed and
does not tell it what the best action would have been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because reinforcement learning is a bit of a niche area in Machine Learning, I
never really got into it when I was new to the field. Still, the fundamental
idea sounded incredibly interesting to me, so in the holidays after the winter
semester I decided to work through this book. This was just in time to read the
reworked second edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book was written by Sutton and Barto who are renowned experts in the field
and came up with many of the most important ideas themselves. While the book
does contain a large amount of math, it’s still very accessible because
everything is explained up from the ground up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working through the book was a lot of fun and I ended up &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/florian/reinforcement-learning&quot;&gt;implementing&lt;/a&gt; many algorithms from the book using Jupyter notebooks.
By now, reinforcement learning is also one of my absolute favorite areas of
machine learning, and the book definitely contributed to this. I still marvel at
the way it builds up the entire framework step by step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-seven-habits-of-highly-effective-people&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Habits-Highly-Effective-People-Powerful/dp/1451639619/&quot;&gt;The Seven Habits of Highly Effective People&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/books-2017/effective.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Seven Habits of Highly Effective People cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book tries to explain what traits most successful people have in common.
The fundamental idea behind the book is that there are seven such habits that
most of these people share.
One chapter is devoted to each habit, in which it is discussed in a lot of detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the first few pages of the book, there is an incredible number of quotes from
well-known people that praise the book. This increased my expectations even
further, but ultimately I really did not like the book. The habits themselves all make
sense but they are discussed in a huge length, which becomes off-putting at some
point. Other advice from the book is way too over-engineered and complicated. I
feel like it would’ve made more sense to write down these ideas in a long essay
rather than 400 page book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-clash-of-kings&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Clash-Kings-Song-Fire-Book/dp/0553579908&quot;&gt;A Clash of Kings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/books-2017/acok.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Clash of Kings cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Clash of Kings&lt;/em&gt; is the second book from the &lt;em&gt;A Song of Ice and Fire&lt;/em&gt; series
that &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; is based on. After I read the first book in 2016, I was
planning to read the other four books this year just so that I would be done
when the sixth book was going to come out. Unfortunately, that book got delayed further
and further and is not even out by now, so I decided to pause again after the second book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I really enjoyed the book. Knowing the important plot points from
the TV series takes some fun away, but the second book already starts to deviate
from the show, so there were still some surprises left. The writing style is
also great and I really like how each chapter is told from the point of view of
a different character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-mathematicians-apology&quot;&gt;A Mathematician’s Apology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short essay, interesting, don’t agree on all points&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people&quot;&gt;How To Win Friends And Influence People&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suggested by most reading lists, a lot of obvious points but generally
interesting to read&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;openintro-statistics&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openintro.org/stat/&quot;&gt;OpenIntro Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/books-2017/openintro-stats.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;OpenIntro Statistics cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having focused my studies on Machine Learning, I felt like I learned a lot
about certain areas of statistics while not touching others at all. At some
point, I decided that I should spent a little bit of time learning the
fundamentals of statistics to be able to get a good overview of the entire
field. Especially significance tests were a part of statistics where I felt like
I really lacked knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OpenIntro Statistics is a freely available textbook that seemed suitable for
this. It makes nearly no assumptions about the prior knowledge of the reader. On
the one hand this is great. You can pick up the book without revising
any other topics beforehand. But it also means that some parts of the book are
incredibly basic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first book where I actively started writing
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/florian/reading-notes/blob/master/1_OpenIntro-Statistics.md&quot;&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt; that
summarize the most important points and concepts. This turned out to be incredibly effective,
and I still can’t believe I never did this in an organized fashion before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I really like that the books cover a large number of different
genres. I also only just noticed that I only read books in English this year.
I’m pretty sure it was the same for 2016, which means I haven’t read a book in
German for at least two years.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4002/reading-2017/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4002/reading-2017/</guid>
        
        
        <category>reading-notes</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
